<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Music Theory III]]></title>
  <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/"/>
  <updated>2013-09-25T07:45:03-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kris Shaffer]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kris.shaffer@colorado.edu]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 9 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-9-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-24T14:49:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-9-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For <em>Thursday, Sept. 26, 8am</em>, do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Read the resources: <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/thoroughbassFigures.html">Introduction to thoroughbass</a>, <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/functions.html">Introduction to musical functions</a>, and <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/harmonicFunctions.html">Harmonic functions</a>.</li>
<li>Take the <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a> quiz with session ID 300963.</li>
<li>Update your self-evaluation, reflecting on two-voice counterpoint, professionalism, <em>and liberal education values</em>. For the latter, make initial comments on how you are applying Long&#8217;s four habits of the liberal arts in your work for this class. (Not all of them will be active at this point, given what we&#8217;ve studied so far and what we haven&#8217;t covered yet.)</li>
</ul>


<p>For <em>Monday, Sept. 30, 9am</em>, get together with your group and compose your third- and fourth-species exercises. Submit your two best exercises for both third and fourth species in Google Drive for feedback. I will not provide feedback on anything turned in later than that. Your final portfolios will be due on Oct. 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 8 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-8-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T11:48:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-8-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 8am on Tuesday, Sept. 24, please do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on fourth-species counterpoint from Monday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/fourthSpecies.html">Composing a fourth-species counterpoint</a>, and watch the videos at the end.</li>
<li>Log on to <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a>, use session ID 747127, and take the short quiz.</li>
</ul>


<p>Before Wednesday&#8217;s class, please review any feedback I provide you individually via Learning Catalytics or collectively on the course website after the quizzes have been completed.</p>

<p><em>Notes on the quiz:</em><br/>
All quizzes in this course are <em>open-note</em>. You are also <em>encouraged</em> to talk to each other, in person or on Piazza, as you work on this quiz. However, be sure that the short-answer responses are 1) short (!), and 2) in your own words.</p>

<p>Please bring all of your notes, examples, and other materials to class on Wednesday, as well as a device that is compatible with Learning Catalytics. (Smart phones, tablets, laptops, or web-friendly e-readers are all fine.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unit I portfolios]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/unit-i-portfolios/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T11:32:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/unit-i-portfolios</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We will begin Unit II as planned on Monday, Sept. 30. However, you will have a little more time to work on your species portfolios. Please pay careful attention to the following schedule and keep on-task with your group. No late submissions will be accepted except in the case of an emergency, and technology problems do not constitute an emergency. You should be more than familiar enough with these tools now.</p>

<ul>
<li>Monday, Sept. 30, 9am: Submit your best two third-species exercises and your best two fourth-species exercises for feedback. Nothing submitted after that time will be given feedback before the final portfolio submission.</li>
<li>Monday, Oct. 7, 9am: Submit your final species portfolio (16 exercises per the Unit II guide).</li>
</ul>


<p>All submissions should be PDF files in your group&#8217;s Google Drive submission folder. Make sure all group members&#8217; last names are in the folder title and on every document you submit.</p>

<p>If you have any issues or questions, contact me well in advance of the deadlines. Keep in mind that I rarely respond to student emails on weekends, especially Sundays.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 7 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-7-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T13:51:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-7-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>By 8am on Thursday, Sept. 19:</em></p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on third-species counterpoint from Monday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/thirdSpecies.html">Composing a third-species counterpoint</a>.</li>
<li>Bring your model third-species examples back to class on Wednesday, labeling two examples of each of the following techniques described in the reading:

<ul>
<li>dissonant passing tone</li>
<li>dissonant neighbor tone</li>
<li>double neighbor</li>
<li>nota cambiata</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>For each work group: Upload your two best second-species exercises thus far to your group&#8217;s Google Drive folder for me to take a look at and give you feedback (in addition to the first-species exercises already in those folders).</li>
</ul>


<p>There is no online quiz for third species.</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 8 (Sept. 23):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza. We will move on to fourth-species analysis on Wednesday.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 6 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-6-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T12:48:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-6-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Work with your group on your shared portfolio of species exercises. I will be happy to comment on the work in your portfolio as you go, but only after everyone in your group has given their own input for the exercise or question that is causing difficulty. (I will give some official feedback before Wednesday on your first- species portfolio in GDrive, and time permitting your second-species progress.)</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 7 (Sept. 18):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza.</p>

<p>Continue the discussion on music, philosophy, and the liberal arts—as far as it interests you—in Piazza. We&#8217;ll return to the topic from time to time as appropriate to the tasks we are performing in class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 5 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-5-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T19:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-5-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>By 8am on Thursday, Sept. 12:</em></p>

<p>Update your self-evaluation concerning the two conceptual areas we have engaged thus far—<em>strict voice-leading</em> and <em>professionalism</em>. Include any relevant information on what you&#8217;ve done in class so far to demonstrate mastery (or progress toward mastery) in those areas. Also, submit your first response to the &#8220;over the weekend&#8221; assignment below.</p>

<p><em>Over the weekend:</em></p>

<p>On Piazza, you will find a post &#8220;Music, Philosophy and the Liberal Arts.&#8221; Read that post, and the linked blog post, and engage on Piazza with your classmates, me, and Chris Long (the author of that blog post) as instructed. This is a great opportunity to interact with a leading scholar of another field at another university in a way that will enrich our understanding of what we are doing at CU in the College of Music. Take full advantage of it.</p>

<p><em>Ongoing:</em></p>

<p>Work with your group on your shared portfolio of species exercises. I will be happy to comment on the work in your portfolio as you go, but only after everyone in your group has given their own input for the exercise or question that is causing difficulty.</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 6 (Sept. 16):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Second-species quiz]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/second-species-quiz/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T15:42:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/second-species-quiz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Following are some general responses to the second-species quiz. Please review before Wednesday&#8217;s meeting.</em></p>

<p>First, a couple of you missed the quiz. Be sure you manage your deadlines properly. For the species counterpoint unit, quizzes will always be due by Tuesday morning. There are no make-up quizzes.</p>

<p>Please review your results in Learning Catalytics. Keep in mind that you are not being scored for a percentage grade. These questions are in part to give you feedback on your understanding before you attempt second-species exercises, and in part to guide your thinking towards certain musical concepts that will carry over into other musical styles we study.</p>

<p>Questions 1–4 were fairly straightforward, and the correct/incorrect indications in Learning Catalytics should help you review that information. General responses to questions 5–7 follow.</p>

<p><strong>5. Large leaps are more common in second-species counterpoint than in first species. Why do you think that is? In other words, are there factors that necessitate more large leaps in second species? and/or Are there attenuating factors in second-species that make large leaps less problematic?</strong></p>

<p>There are two main reasons for this. First, more large leaps are <em>needed</em> to add variety to the texture. All steps and a few small leaps would lead to monotony, given how many more notes there are in a second-species counterpoint line.</p>

<p>Second, we have more freedom in second species to use leaps because some of the constraints of first species are gone. For instance, in first species, all leaps would take place when both voices move, making them stand out more, which reduces smoothness. In second species, leaps <em>within a bar</em> don&#8217;t detract from smoothness as much, and so they fit in to the texture better than first species, leading to them being more common.</p>

<p><strong>6. Why do you think it is preferable to begin a second-species counterpoint with a half rest rather than two half notes?</strong></p>

<p>Many of you picked up that it is easier to write a second-species counterpoint line when beginning with a half note. While being easier may lead to less problems, and thus a better sounding counterpoint line, that&#8217;s not the <em>musical</em> reason why it is preferable to begin with a half rest. The musical reason, which a few of you picked up on, is that it adds to the independence of the melodic lines. The half rest is not necessary in order for the lines to sound independent; however, it does enhance that independence, and thus is the more common way to begin a second-species exercise.</p>

<p><strong>7. Why do you think it is common for a second-species counterpoint to have a whole note in the penultimate (next-to-last) bar?</strong></p>

<p>As a number of you noted, the whole note in the penultimate bar emphasizes the coming cadence. By breaking the pattern of half notes, it introduces a degree of tension that resolves with the final cadence, and by slowing down the rhythm of the counterpoint, it signals an ending is coming.</p>

<p>The whole note, however, has nothing to do with avoiding dissonance or achieving stepwise, contrary motion. All of those things can be accomplished by two half notes, as well, with a properly crafted line. In fact, as you will find in your composing, your decision whether to use a whole note or two half notes will depend largely on the intervals formed as your cantus firmus and counterpoint approach the penultimate bar. If one rhythm makes better melodic and harmonic intervals than the other, use it. If they are equally good intervallically, use a whole note.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 4 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-4-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-06T10:24:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-4-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 8am on Tuesday, Sept. 10, please do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on second-species counterpoint from Monday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/secondSpecies.html">Composing a second-species counterpoint</a>, and watch the video at the end.</li>
<li>Log on to <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a>, use session ID 76824, and take the short quiz.</li>
<li>For each work group: Create a Google Drive folder with <em>all students&#8217; last names</em> in its title. Share it with everyone in the group, and with me. Upload your two best first-species exercises thus far for me to take a look at and give you feedback.</li>
</ul>


<p>Before Wednesday&#8217;s class, please review any feedback I provide you individually via Learning Catalytics or collectively on the course website after the quizzes have been completed.</p>

<p><em>Notes on the quiz:</em><br/>
All quizzes in this course are <em>open-note</em>. You are also <em>encouraged</em> to talk to each other, in person or on Piazza, as you work on this quiz. However, be sure that the short-answer responses are 1) short (!), and 2) in your own words.</p>

<p>Be sure to bring manuscript paper and a pencil, or a laptop/tablet with music notation software, to class on Wednesday. (I highly recommend <a href="http://www.musescore.org">MuseScore</a>, <a href="http://www.noteflight.com">NoteFlight</a>, and <a href="http://www.lilypond.org">Lilypond</a>—all free, all with different strengths.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 3 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-3-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-03T13:12:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-3-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>By 8am on Thursday, Sept. 4:</em></p>

<p>Update your self-evaluation concerning the two conceptual areas we have engaged thus far—<em>strict voice-leading</em> and <em>professionalism</em>. Include any relevant information on what you&#8217;ve done in class so far to demonstrate mastery (or progress toward mastery) in those areas.</p>

<p><em>Ongoing:</em></p>

<p>Work with your group on your shared portfolio of species exercises. It is a good idea to try to finish each species as we go (one species, four exercises, per week) in order to stay on schedule for submitting a solid, complete portfolio at the end of the unit. Consider using Google Drive as a place to store your finshed exercises, as well as your in-progress work, so every group member has access to the entire portfolio at all times. I will be happy to comment on the work in your portfolio as you go, but only after everyone in your group has given their own input for the exercise or question that is causing difficulty.</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 4 (Sept. 9):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza. We will repeat last week&#8217;s analysis exercise but for second species counterpoint this time.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 3 info]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/meeting-3-info/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T10:04:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/meeting-3-info</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have looked through the Learning Catalytics quizzes. Please log in to see specific comments from me on some of your answers, and see the <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/notes-on-first-species-quiz/">previous post</a> for some general comments on the quiz that will help guide your composition and analysis throughout this unit.</p>

<p>On Wednesday, we will begin class getting your self-evaluation forms set up. If you are at all reticent or confused when it comes to these technological things, please bring your laptop/tablet to make sure you have it set up correctly before you leave class.</p>

<p>The rest of the class time will be devoted to composing. Be sure to bring manuscript paper and a pencil, or a laptop/tablet with notation software installed and ready to go, to class on Wednesday.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Notes on first-species quiz]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/notes-on-first-species-quiz/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-30T09:30:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/notes-on-first-species-quiz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have now closed the quiz on Learning Catalytics. Below are some general comments on specific questions that I would like you all to read and ponder before Wednesday&#8217;s class, when we will compose some first-species exercises. Also, I have left some of you specific comments on your quiz answers. Please log in to Learning Catalytics and review the results of the quiz to see those comments. Keep in mind that this quiz is not graded as a percentage that factors into a final average. It is a pedagogical tool meant to get you to think about certain key concepts. If your quiz demonstrated good conceptual knowledge you can cite it in your self-evaluation at the end of the unit. If not, seek to demonstrate that knowledge through subsequent activities (further quizzes, compositional exercises, Piazza discussions, etc.).</p>

<h3>3) Rank the types of motion found in first-speices counterpoint according to how common they are.</h3>

<p>No one counted the intervals in the example solutions to obtain the answer! As those examples show, oblique is less common than similar, similar less common than parallel, parallel less common than contrary. If you put similar = parallel, I marked it correct, since that is very close.</p>

<p>I think the confusing issue here is that the constraints on parallel motion you have learned have been in terms of hard rules (and lots of red ink when they occur!). However, since those constraints involve the least common intervals in first species (perfect consonances), and since those constraints <em>also</em> involve similar motion in first-species (perfect consonances must not be approached by parallel <em>or</em> similar motion), those constraints don&#8217;t make similar motion more common in first species. Further, the preference for stepwise motion means that parallel is more likely than similar motion (which always involves at least one leap).</p>

<p>Think for a second about <em>how</em> one moves in similar motion in first species. The arrival must be on an imperfect consonance (3rd/6th). Let&#8217;s use do–mi as an example. If the upper voice steps re–mi, what must the lower voice do to obtain similar motion? Ti–do would be parallel; la–do would mean starting on a forbidden dissonance (la–re, a P4); sol–do in the lower voice would create a P5 moving to a M3—allowable similar motion. But what does that involve? A relatively uncommon leap of a fourth in the lower voice. The only other options for similar motion here involve even larger leaps. In most cases in first species, similar motion will involve at least one leap larger than a third. Since those leaps are relatively uncommon, so will similar motion be relatively uncommon.</p>

<h3>5) Why do you think perfect consonances are called &#8220;perfect&#8221;?</h3>

<p>Two notes: First, many of you made scientific explanations based on interval ratios, etc., but none made a historical/linguistic argument. That&#8217;s where the real answer lies. In Latin (like Greek and many other older Western languages), the concepts of &#8220;perfection&#8221; (lacking flaws) and &#8220;completion&#8221; (lacking nothing) are united in a single word, and therefore concept. Thus, the word <a href="http://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/perfectus"><em>perfectus</em></a> can mean &#8220;complete&#8221; just as easily as it can mean &#8220;pure&#8221; or &#8220;mistake-free.&#8221; Because of the acoustical stability of perfect consonances, they are the intervals preferred for endings of musical pieces (in pre-Classical music), and therefore two-voice exercises. Since they are the intervals of ending, they are the intervals signalling completeness, and therefore perfection. Inperfect consonances do not signal completeness, but motion and the need for something more stable to follow. Therefore, they are imperfect—not because they are flawed in some way, but because they do not signal finality.</p>

<h3>6) Why do you think parallel perfect consonances should be avoided?</h3>

<p>Because of the above, perfect consonances should be generally avoided in the middle of a species exercise as it is. Using two in a row also reduces independence of line through parallel motion, at the same time as an arrest of motion mid-exercise (because of the stability/finality of the perfect consonances), and uses intervals that stand out of the musical texture. All these things together also reduce the smoothness and evenness of the exercise. For these reasons (lack of melodic independence, arresting of motion, drawing attention to a moment mid-phrase), parallel perfect consonances are to be avoided.</p>

<p>Note that in many musical situations, these priorities hold, as do the effects of using parallel perfect consonances in that context. However, in some musical styles, there are different priorities, and in some musical textures, parallel perfect intervals do not have these effects. That is for the difference in &#8220;rules&#8221; between musical styles. One needs to be sensitive to the priorities of a given style and the effects that different compositional devices have in relation to those priorities.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 2 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/meeting-2-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-27T10:14:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/meeting-2-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 8am on Thursday, August 29, please do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on first-species counterpoint from Wednesday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/firstSpecies.html">Composing a first-species counterpoint</a>, and watch the video at the end.</li>
<li>Log on to <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a>, use session ID 632054, and take the short quiz.</li>
</ul>


<p>Before 8am on Tuesday, Sept. 3, please:</p>

<ul>
<li>Make a 1–2 minute video introducing yourself: Who are you? Where are you from? What are your goals? (in life, and in this class) This will help me get to know you better. Upload to Google Drive, and share with me.</li>
</ul>


<p><em>Notes on the quiz:</em><br/>
All quizzes in this course are <em>open-note</em>. You are also <em>encouraged</em> to talk to each other, in person or on Piazza, as you work on this quiz. However, be sure that the short-answer responses are 1) short (!), and 2) in your own words.</p>

<p>Since we have a day off on Monday, be sure to review the reading and your quiz responses (and any feedback I send you) before class next Wednesday.</p>

<p>Be sure to bring manuscript paper and a pencil, or a laptop/tablet with music notation software, to class on Wednesday. (I highly recommend <a href="http://www.musescore.org">MuseScore</a>, <a href="http://www.noteflight.com">NoteFlight</a>, and <a href="http://www.lilypond.org">Lilypond</a>—all free, all with different strengths.)</p>

<p>A 1-minute video domonstrating uploading and sharing files on Google Drive can be found <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/GDrive.html">here</a>. If you have any difficulties, please make use of Piazza to ask questions of me and/or your classmates. CU officially supports GDrive, so the student help desk should also be able to help.</p>

<p>If you have any questions, please ask them on Piazza.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 1 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/meeting-1-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-24T19:47:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/meeting-1-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before our next meeting (Wednesday, Aug. 28), sign up for <a href="http://www.learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a> and <a href="http://www.piazza.com">Piazza</a> (if you didn&#8217;t already). Also, read the following resources: <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/speciesIntro.html">introduction to strict voice-leading</a> and <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/cantusFirmus.html">composing a <em>cantus firmus</em></a>.</p>

<p>Please make use of Piazza, rather than emailing me directly, if you have any questions about the reading, the course, the syllabus, the policies, the homework, or the technology.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[For Monday, August 26 (first meeting)]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/for-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T11:19:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/for-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome (back) to Boulder!</p>

<p>Before our first meeting, please read the <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/syllabus/">syllabus</a>, <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/assessment/">assessment</a>, <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/coursework/">coursework</a>, and <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/policies/">policies</a> pages for this course, as well as the <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/units/unit1.html">Unit I guide</a>. Note any questions you have about these documents.</p>

<p>Also, please bring a web-enabled device to class, such as a smartphone, tablet, or laptop.</p>

<p>I look forward to meeting all of you on Monday!</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Piazza]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/piazza/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-20T10:53:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/piazza</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This term we will be using Piazza for class discussion. The system is highly catered to getting you help fast and efficiently from classmates and myself. Rather than emailing questions about course materials directly to me, I encourage you to post your questions on Piazza. If you have any problems or feedback for the developers, email <a href="mailto:team@piazza.com">team@piazza.com</a>.</p>

<p>Of course, matters of a private nature should <em>not</em> be addressed on Piazza. Please email me about private concerns, or better yet, come by my office so we can discuss them in person.</p>

<p>Find our class Piazza page at: <a href="https://piazza.com/colorado/fall2013/musc2101001/home">https://piazza.com/colorado/fall2013/musc2101001/home</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/welcome/"/>
    <updated>2013-08-08T20:09:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/08/welcome</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>This is the website for Semester 3 Theory at CU–Boulder&#8217;s College of Music, Section 1 with Kris Shaffer. More info coming soon.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
