<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Music Theory III]]></title>
  <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/"/>
  <updated>2013-10-24T10:42:24-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Kris Shaffer]]></name>
    <email><![CDATA[kris.shaffer@colorado.edu]]></email>
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Week 10 &amp; Unit II primers]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/week-10-and-unit-ii-primers/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-24T10:26:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/week-10-and-unit-ii-primers</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>By Monday, Nov. 4, 9am</em>:</p>

<p>Finish your final keyboard-style voice-leading primers with your group. The primers should be written in clean, grammatical prose, and they should include information on <em>voicing</em> and <em>motion</em> for all diatonic chords and all common chromatic chords (Neapolitan, augmented-sixth chords, and applied chords) in <em>basso continuo</em> and <em>melodic</em> keyboard style. You have resources in Google Drive that we collaborated on in class for some of these principles. Use them to guide your work, but be sure to put everything in your own words.</p>

<p>Class time on Wednesday will be reserved for work on this, so be sure to make good use of that time. Kellan will be present to answer some questions as you work. I will be at a conference on Wednesday, but will be available on Piazza. Please direct all questions for me there. I will not be checking my CU email frequently while at my conference.</p>

<p>This is your end-of-unit project submission, so make sure it is solid. Catch up where you need to, and make sure it is written in excellent prose. And by all means, include musical examples in your text where helpful. I have made <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/createGraphic.html">a resource</a> that can help you do that.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prep for Oct. 28]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/prep-for-oct-28/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-22T10:43:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/prep-for-oct-28</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 7am on Monday, Oct. 28, work with your group either in person or online via Google Drive, and expand your voice-leading primer to include information about voicing and motion with <em>chromatic chords</em> (chromatically altered subdominants and applied chords) based on the information from your readings and the examples in your basso continuo and melodic-style models. Also, take the opportunity to clean up, correct, and/or condense the information you already have in your primer. Finally, copy and paste your principles of <em>melodic-style voice-leading</em> into the document in the MUSC 2101 Shared Materials folder, leaving out any that duplicate the principles already pasted in.</p>

<p>On Monday, we will use Google Drive to perform another whole-class consolidation and evaluation of the principles you&#8217;ve all found so far in your groups, using the shared melodic-style Google document as our basis. Please bring a Google-Driv-compatible device to class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prep for Oct. 23]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/prep-for-oct-23/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-18T12:57:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/prep-for-oct-23</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before Wednesday&#8217;s meeting, read the resources on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/alteredSubdominants.html">Chromatically Altered Subdominants</a>, <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/appliedChords.html">Applied Chords</a>, and <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/modalMixture.html">Modal Mixture</a>. Bring a Google-Drive-enabled device to class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[For Monday, Oct. 21]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/for-monday/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-18T12:56:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/for-monday</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Please bring the melodic keyboard-style models to class on Monday, as well as something to write with and on.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Asst. for Fri., Oct. 18]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/asst-for-fri/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-15T09:54:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/asst-for-fri</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 8am on Friday, work with your group (in person, or online) to clean up your primer in Google Drive. Your primer thus far should include:</p>

<ul>
<li>a concise set of principles for chord voicing in basso continuo style</li>
<li>a consise set of principles for motion (of notes from one chord to the next) in basso continuo style</li>
<li>a concise explanation of the differences between chord voicing in basso continuo style and melodic style</li>
<li>a concise explanation of the differences between principles of motion in basso continuo style and melodic style</li>
</ul>


<p>I will announce on Friday, after reviewing these, what you should bring to class on Monday (probably staff paper and/or a device for Google Drive or Learning Catalytics). There will be no additional assignment, but I may post some resources that would be helpful for review over the weekend.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prep &amp; assignment for Oct. 16]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/prep-and-assignment-for-oct-16/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-10T11:49:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/prep-and-assignment-for-oct-16</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before Wednesday&#8217;s class, revise your group&#8217;s primer in Google docs with the basic principles of <em>basso continuo</em> voice-leading discussed in Monday&#8217;s class. You may incorporate principles and ideas discussed in class or shared by your classmates, but you must express those ideas in your own words in your group&#8217;s primer.</p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class on Wednesday for working in Google Drive.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Assignment for Oct. 14]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/assignment-for-oct-14/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-08T11:28:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/assignment-for-oct-14</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Form a group of 2–4 students that will work together on the Unit II portfolio. Using the template provided during class (available in <a href="https://drive.google.com/a/colorado.edu/folderview?id=0B9o4hmKNoi6cXzNiQlpRM0o5UXc&amp;usp=sharing">Google Drive</a>), create a document where you will build your primer on keyboard-style voice leading.</p>

<p>Using the <a href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/media/modelBassoContinuo-withFuncBass.pdf">model basso-continuo style voice-leading examples</a> distributed in class, work with that group to discern the principles according to which those examples are realized from the figured bass line. Focus on two main issues: <em>chord voicing</em> (what notes go into the chord and which are doubled/left out) and <em>motion</em> (how do individual pitches in one chord progress to the pitches in the next chord).</p>

<p>For Monday, try to come up with <em>five</em> or less principles that cover all situations relating to <em>chord voicing</em>, and <em>three</em> or less principles that cover all sitations relating to <em>motion</em>. Each principle should be expressed in clear, grammatically correct sentences in your Google document, not bullet points.</p>

<p>Do as much as you can within your group, but feel free to consult other groups on Piazza if you get stuck.</p>

<p>Also, please watch the following video (approx. 15 min) as you continue to solidify your understanding of harmonic functional analysis. In it, I walk through the excerpt from Haydn XVI:35 that we analyzed in class on Monday.</p>

<iframe src="http://player.vimeo.com/video/76469959" width="500" height="375" frameborder="0" webkitallowfullscreen mozallowfullscreen allowfullscreen></iframe>


<p> <p><a href="http://vimeo.com/76469959">Functional analysis of Haydn XVI:35, I., mm. 1–8</a> from <a href="http://vimeo.com/user11692346">Kris Shaffer</a> on <a href="https://vimeo.com">Vimeo</a>.</p></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prep for Oct. 9]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/meeting-12-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-04T13:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/meeting-12-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before class on Oct. 9, please do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Read the new resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/harmonicAnalysis.html">Harmonic analysis</a>, and write down any questions you have about it and bring them to class.</li>
<li>Review any functional-bass materials that have caused you confusion (readngs and Learning Catalytics quizzes or class activities).</li>
<li>Bring a device that will allow you to work in Google Drive (a laptop, or a tablet <em>with the Google Drive app installed</em>). We will work there instead of Piazza on Wednesday for our analysis activity.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 11 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/meeting-11-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T12:25:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/meeting-11-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For <em>Monday, Oct. 7</em>, do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Submit your complete Unit I species counterpoint portfolio in your group&#8217;s submissions folder on Google Drive. Make sure the final portfolio is clearly labeled, either as a single PDF file, or a folder containing the various PDF files.</li>
<li>Submit an updated self-evaluation that includes a grade for two-voice counterpoint and a grade for professionalism, along with <em>detailed</em> comments (1–2 paragraphs) that reference specific reasons for the grades you chose. These should include things like counterpoints in your group portfolio that you composed or offered significant corrections to, insights expressed on quizzes, Piazza, or in class, etc.</li>
<li>Read the Unit II guide (link to the right) and come to class on Monday with any questions about it.</li>
</ul>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Harmonic syntax quiz response]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/harmonic-syntax-quiz-response/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T11:08:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/harmonic-syntax-quiz-response</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Below are some responses to common misconceptions on the quiz. We will discuss some of this in class on Wednesday.</p>

<h2>Cadence definitions</h2>

<p>Some of you are confused as to the definition of <em>perfect authentic cadence</em> and <em>imperfect authentic cadence</em>. This may be because of an error in the Clendinning/Marvin text you used last year. Those authors include inverted chords in the category of IAC. However, historical theorists and composers did not consider things like V–I6 or V6–I to be cadences, nor do most theorists today who are leading the study of musical form. Both perfect and imperfect authentic cadences <em>always</em> have <em>sol</em>–<em>do</em> as their bass, and the functional bass for both is always <strong>D5 T1</strong>. The only difference is in the melody.</p>

<h2>5) Why do you think a <em>perfect authentic cadence</em> is called &#8220;perfect&#8221; and an <em>imperfect authentic cadence</em> is called &#8220;imperfect&#8221;?</h2>

<p>This is the same as species counterpoint. While both, by definition of a cadence, can end a phrase, only a perfect cadence will end, or complete, a typical classical work. (Remember that &#8220;perfectus&#8221; means &#8220;complete.&#8221;) This is because is has more of a closed or final sound than the IAC. (Though, again, keep in mind that both have the same bass pattern.)</p>

<h2>7) Explain prolongation as best you can in a single sentence.</h2>

<p>Prolongation extends a harmonic function by means of embellishment (either a voice-leading embellishment, a &#8220;contrapuntal chord,&#8221; or a subsidiary harmonic progression), allowing more elaborate harmonic phrases while still maintaining a <em>single</em> <strong>T S D T</strong> progression.</p>

<h2>10) Attempt an <em>interpreted</em> functional bass analysis of the following progression:</h2>

<blockquote><p><strong>T1 D7 T1 D2 T3 S4 D5 T1</strong></p></blockquote>

<p>Answer: <strong>T(1 D7n 1 D2p 3) S4 D5 T1</strong></p>

<p>Tonic function (the most common function to be prolonged) is prolonged by two passing chords: <strong>D7</strong> and <strong>D2</strong>. Since the <em>ti</em> bass note of <strong>D7</strong> functions as a neighbor to the <em>do</em> of the <strong>T1</strong> chords, <strong>D7</strong> is a neighbor chord (<strong>D7n</strong>). Since the <em>re</em> of the <strong>D2</strong> chord functions as a passing tone between the <em>do</em> and <em>mi</em> of the <strong>T1</strong> and <strong>T3</strong> chords, the <strong>D2</strong> chord is a passing chord (<strong>D2p</strong>).</p>

<p>Two general rules of thumb come in to play here: <strong>S4 D5 T1</strong> at the end of a phrase is <em>always</em> the cadential progression, and prefer to analyze a tonic prolongation as long as makes musical sense.</p>

<p>Don&#8217;t sweat this one too much. It&#8217;s all very abstract still, with no real music in front of you. I mainly wanted to get you thinking about this before we see real musical examples in the near future. It will make a lot more sense once you get more familiar with it and start connecting it to musical form and analysis, but only if you have some vague notion of the concepts first.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Species portfolio feedback]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/species-portfolio-feedback/"/>
    <updated>2013-10-01T10:22:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/10/species-portfolio-feedback</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>I have provided feedback to all fourth-species submissions in your Google Drive folders where you submitted them. Please review those notes and update your portfolio as necessary before Monday. Also, if you did not receive feedback for first species because of a file format issue, I have not provided you feedback on those, as well.</p>

<p>Kellan should be getting you feedback on third species by Wednesday or Thursday.</p>

<p>If you did not submit third- or fourth-species exercises yesterday, you will not receive any feedback on those species, even during office hours, before the final portfolio is due on Oct. 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 10 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-10-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-26T15:15:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-10-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For <em>Tuesday, Oct. 1, 8am</em>, do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Read the resources: <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/harmonicSyntax.html">Harmonic syntax</a> and <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/cadenceTypes.html">Classical cadence types</a>.</li>
<li>Take the <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a> quiz with session ID 396102.</li>
</ul>


<p>Bring a Learning Catalytics capable device to class on Wednesday for more group-based activity.</p>

<p>Continue to work on your species counterpoint porfolios, which are due Monday, Oct. 7. Be sure to make revisions based on the feedback you receive and put everything in notation software before the deadline.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 9 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-9-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-24T14:49:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-9-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For <em>Thursday, Sept. 26, 8am</em>, do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Read the resources: <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/thoroughbassFigures.html">Introduction to thoroughbass</a>, <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/functions.html">Introduction to musical functions</a>, and <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/harmonicFunctions.html">Harmonic functions</a>.</li>
<li>Take the <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a> quiz with session ID 300963.</li>
<li>Update your self-evaluation, reflecting on two-voice counterpoint, professionalism, <em>and liberal education values</em>. For the latter, make initial comments on how you are applying Long&#8217;s four habits of the liberal arts in your work for this class. (Not all of them will be active at this point, given what we&#8217;ve studied so far and what we haven&#8217;t covered yet.)</li>
</ul>


<p>For <em>Monday, Sept. 30, 9am</em>, get together with your group and compose your third- and fourth-species exercises. Submit your two best exercises for both third and fourth species in Google Drive for feedback. I will not provide feedback on anything turned in later than that. Your final portfolios will be due on Oct. 7.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 8 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-8-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T11:48:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-8-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 8am on Tuesday, Sept. 24, please do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on fourth-species counterpoint from Monday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/fourthSpecies.html">Composing a fourth-species counterpoint</a>, and watch the videos at the end.</li>
<li>Log on to <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a>, use session ID 747127, and take the short quiz.</li>
</ul>


<p>Before Wednesday&#8217;s class, please review any feedback I provide you individually via Learning Catalytics or collectively on the course website after the quizzes have been completed.</p>

<p><em>Notes on the quiz:</em><br/>
All quizzes in this course are <em>open-note</em>. You are also <em>encouraged</em> to talk to each other, in person or on Piazza, as you work on this quiz. However, be sure that the short-answer responses are 1) short (!), and 2) in your own words.</p>

<p>Please bring all of your notes, examples, and other materials to class on Wednesday, as well as a device that is compatible with Learning Catalytics. (Smart phones, tablets, laptops, or web-friendly e-readers are all fine.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unit I portfolios]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/unit-i-portfolios/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-20T11:32:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/unit-i-portfolios</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>We will begin Unit II as planned on Monday, Sept. 30. However, you will have a little more time to work on your species portfolios. Please pay careful attention to the following schedule and keep on-task with your group. No late submissions will be accepted except in the case of an emergency, and technology problems do not constitute an emergency. You should be more than familiar enough with these tools now.</p>

<ul>
<li>Monday, Sept. 30, 9am: Submit your best two third-species exercises and your best two fourth-species exercises for feedback. Nothing submitted after that time will be given feedback before the final portfolio submission.</li>
<li>Monday, Oct. 7, 9am: Submit your final species portfolio (16 exercises per the Unit II guide).</li>
</ul>


<p>All submissions should be PDF files in your group&#8217;s Google Drive submission folder. Make sure all group members&#8217; last names are in the folder title and on every document you submit.</p>

<p>If you have any issues or questions, contact me well in advance of the deadlines. Keep in mind that I rarely respond to student emails on weekends, especially Sundays.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 7 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-7-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-17T13:51:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-7-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>By 8am on Thursday, Sept. 19:</em></p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on third-species counterpoint from Monday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/thirdSpecies.html">Composing a third-species counterpoint</a>.</li>
<li>Bring your model third-species examples back to class on Wednesday, labeling two examples of each of the following techniques described in the reading:

<ul>
<li>dissonant passing tone</li>
<li>dissonant neighbor tone</li>
<li>double neighbor</li>
<li>nota cambiata</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>For each work group: Upload your two best second-species exercises thus far to your group&#8217;s Google Drive folder for me to take a look at and give you feedback (in addition to the first-species exercises already in those folders).</li>
</ul>


<p>There is no online quiz for third species.</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 8 (Sept. 23):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza. We will move on to fourth-species analysis on Wednesday.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 6 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-6-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-16T12:48:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-6-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Work with your group on your shared portfolio of species exercises. I will be happy to comment on the work in your portfolio as you go, but only after everyone in your group has given their own input for the exercise or question that is causing difficulty. (I will give some official feedback before Wednesday on your first- species portfolio in GDrive, and time permitting your second-species progress.)</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 7 (Sept. 18):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza.</p>

<p>Continue the discussion on music, philosophy, and the liberal arts—as far as it interests you—in Piazza. We&#8217;ll return to the topic from time to time as appropriate to the tasks we are performing in class.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 5 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-5-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T19:45:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-5-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>By 8am on Thursday, Sept. 12:</em></p>

<p>Update your self-evaluation concerning the two conceptual areas we have engaged thus far—<em>strict voice-leading</em> and <em>professionalism</em>. Include any relevant information on what you&#8217;ve done in class so far to demonstrate mastery (or progress toward mastery) in those areas. Also, submit your first response to the &#8220;over the weekend&#8221; assignment below.</p>

<p><em>Over the weekend:</em></p>

<p>On Piazza, you will find a post &#8220;Music, Philosophy and the Liberal Arts.&#8221; Read that post, and the linked blog post, and engage on Piazza with your classmates, me, and Chris Long (the author of that blog post) as instructed. This is a great opportunity to interact with a leading scholar of another field at another university in a way that will enrich our understanding of what we are doing at CU in the College of Music. Take full advantage of it.</p>

<p><em>Ongoing:</em></p>

<p>Work with your group on your shared portfolio of species exercises. I will be happy to comment on the work in your portfolio as you go, but only after everyone in your group has given their own input for the exercise or question that is causing difficulty.</p>

<p><em>For Meeting 6 (Sept. 16):</em></p>

<p>Be sure to bring a device to class that will allow you to work in Piazza.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Second-species quiz]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/second-species-quiz/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-10T15:42:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/second-species-quiz</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><em>Following are some general responses to the second-species quiz. Please review before Wednesday&#8217;s meeting.</em></p>

<p>First, a couple of you missed the quiz. Be sure you manage your deadlines properly. For the species counterpoint unit, quizzes will always be due by Tuesday morning. There are no make-up quizzes.</p>

<p>Please review your results in Learning Catalytics. Keep in mind that you are not being scored for a percentage grade. These questions are in part to give you feedback on your understanding before you attempt second-species exercises, and in part to guide your thinking towards certain musical concepts that will carry over into other musical styles we study.</p>

<p>Questions 1–4 were fairly straightforward, and the correct/incorrect indications in Learning Catalytics should help you review that information. General responses to questions 5–7 follow.</p>

<p><strong>5. Large leaps are more common in second-species counterpoint than in first species. Why do you think that is? In other words, are there factors that necessitate more large leaps in second species? and/or Are there attenuating factors in second-species that make large leaps less problematic?</strong></p>

<p>There are two main reasons for this. First, more large leaps are <em>needed</em> to add variety to the texture. All steps and a few small leaps would lead to monotony, given how many more notes there are in a second-species counterpoint line.</p>

<p>Second, we have more freedom in second species to use leaps because some of the constraints of first species are gone. For instance, in first species, all leaps would take place when both voices move, making them stand out more, which reduces smoothness. In second species, leaps <em>within a bar</em> don&#8217;t detract from smoothness as much, and so they fit in to the texture better than first species, leading to them being more common.</p>

<p><strong>6. Why do you think it is preferable to begin a second-species counterpoint with a half rest rather than two half notes?</strong></p>

<p>Many of you picked up that it is easier to write a second-species counterpoint line when beginning with a half note. While being easier may lead to less problems, and thus a better sounding counterpoint line, that&#8217;s not the <em>musical</em> reason why it is preferable to begin with a half rest. The musical reason, which a few of you picked up on, is that it adds to the independence of the melodic lines. The half rest is not necessary in order for the lines to sound independent; however, it does enhance that independence, and thus is the more common way to begin a second-species exercise.</p>

<p><strong>7. Why do you think it is common for a second-species counterpoint to have a whole note in the penultimate (next-to-last) bar?</strong></p>

<p>As a number of you noted, the whole note in the penultimate bar emphasizes the coming cadence. By breaking the pattern of half notes, it introduces a degree of tension that resolves with the final cadence, and by slowing down the rhythm of the counterpoint, it signals an ending is coming.</p>

<p>The whole note, however, has nothing to do with avoiding dissonance or achieving stepwise, contrary motion. All of those things can be accomplished by two half notes, as well, with a properly crafted line. In fact, as you will find in your composing, your decision whether to use a whole note or two half notes will depend largely on the intervals formed as your cantus firmus and counterpoint approach the penultimate bar. If one rhythm makes better melodic and harmonic intervals than the other, use it. If they are equally good intervallically, use a whole note.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Meeting 4 assignment]]></title>
    <link href="http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-4-assignment/"/>
    <updated>2013-09-06T10:24:00-06:00</updated>
    <id>http://CUTheory.github.com/theory3/2013/09/meeting-4-assignment</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Before 8am on Tuesday, Sept. 10, please do the following:</p>

<ul>
<li>Review the discussion on second-species counterpoint from Monday&#8217;s class on Piazza.</li>
<li>Read the resource on <a href="http://kris.shaffermusic.com/musicianship/secondSpecies.html">Composing a second-species counterpoint</a>, and watch the video at the end.</li>
<li>Log on to <a href="http://learningcatalytics.com">Learning Catalytics</a>, use session ID 76824, and take the short quiz.</li>
<li>For each work group: Create a Google Drive folder with <em>all students&#8217; last names</em> in its title. Share it with everyone in the group, and with me. Upload your two best first-species exercises thus far for me to take a look at and give you feedback.</li>
</ul>


<p>Before Wednesday&#8217;s class, please review any feedback I provide you individually via Learning Catalytics or collectively on the course website after the quizzes have been completed.</p>

<p><em>Notes on the quiz:</em><br/>
All quizzes in this course are <em>open-note</em>. You are also <em>encouraged</em> to talk to each other, in person or on Piazza, as you work on this quiz. However, be sure that the short-answer responses are 1) short (!), and 2) in your own words.</p>

<p>Be sure to bring manuscript paper and a pencil, or a laptop/tablet with music notation software, to class on Wednesday. (I highly recommend <a href="http://www.musescore.org">MuseScore</a>, <a href="http://www.noteflight.com">NoteFlight</a>, and <a href="http://www.lilypond.org">Lilypond</a>—all free, all with different strengths.)</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
